Joey Chiao-Yin Hsiao

jcyhsiao@umich.edu • +1 (734) 730-0963 • http://joeyhsiao.info 4365 N. Quad, 105 S. State St., Ann Arbor, MI 48109, USA

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests are Human-Computer Interaction (HCI), Computer-Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW), and Social Computing. I employ qualitative and quantitative research methods to investigate sociotechnical factors that affect newcomer's online trust in local exchange of items and services.

EDUCATION

University of Michigan

Ann Arbor, MI, USA 09/2015 - 04/2021 (anticipated) Ph.D in Information

Taipei, Taiwan

09/2010 - 06/2013

Advisor: Dr. Tawanna R. Dillahunt

National Taiwan University M.S. in Computer Science

Advisor: Dr. Jane Yung-Jen Hsu

Carnegie Mellon University (Silicon Valley Campus) Moffett Field, CA, USA 07/2012 - 09/2012

Visiting Student Advisor: Dr. Ted Selker

National Taiwan University Taipei, Taiwan 09/2006 - 06/2010

B.S. in Computer Science

PUBLICATIONS

Peer-Reviewed Journal Articles

[J1] Hsiao, J. C.-Y. and Dillahunt, T. R. (2018). Technology to Support Immigrant Access to Social Capital and Adaptation to a New Country. Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction, Vol. 2, CSCW, Article 70. (acceptance rate: 25.6%).

Peer-Reviewed Conference Proceeding Papers

- [C6] Dillahunt, T. R. and Hsiao, J. C.-Y. (2021). Skills Identifier: A Tool to Promote Career Identity and Self-efficacy Among Underrepresented Job Seekers. To appear in Proc. of The Annual Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences (HICSS '21).
- [C5] Dillahunt, T. R. and Hsiao, J. C.-Y. (2020). Positive Feedback and Self-reflection: Features to Support Self-efficacy among Underrepresented Job Seekers. To appear in Proc. of The ACM CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems 2020 (CHI '20) (acceptance rate: 24.3%).
- [C4] Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Moser, C., Schoenebeck, S., and Dillahunt, T. R. (2018). The Role of Demographics, Trust, Computer Self-efficacy, and Ease of Use in the Sharing Economy. In Proc. of the 1st ACM SIGCAS Conference on Computing and Sustainable Societies (COMPASS '18), Article 37 (Presenter).
- [C3] Hsiao, J. C.-Y., and Dillahunt, T. R. (2017). People-Nearby Applications: How Newcomers Move Their Relationships Offline and Develop Social and Cultural Capital. In Proc. of the 2017 ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW '17), 26-40 (acceptance rate: 33%; Presenter).
- [C2] Rajan, R., Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Lahoti, D., and Selker, T. (2013). "Roger that!" The Value of Adding Social Feedback in Audio-mediated Communications. In Proc. of IFIP TC.13 International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction 2013 (INTERACT '13), 471-488 (acceptance rate: 31%).
- [C1] Tsai, W.-C., Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Lee, H.-C., Huang, C.-H., Hu, J.-C., Liang, R.-H., and Hsu, Y.-J. (2013). Designing a Reminiscence Aid in Personal Soundscape. In Proc. of International Association of Societies of Design Research 2013 (IASDR '13), 5150-5160.

Posters, Workshop Papers, and Presentations

- [P8] Hsiao, J. C.-Y. (2019) Fostering Immigrants' Trust in Online Local Social Exchange. Presented at The 22nd ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW '19), Doctoral Consortium (Presenter).
- [P7] Haimson, O. L., Semaan, B., Dym, B., Hsiao, J. C.-Y, Herron, D., and Moncur, W. (2019) Life Transitions and Social Technologies: Research and Design for Times of Life Change. Workshop at The 22nd ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW '19).

Posters, Workshop Papers, and Presentations (Cont.)

- [P6] Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Dillahunt, T. R. (2017) Detecting Life Changes: Increasing Opportunities to Benefit from People-Nearby Applications. In Proc. of *The ACM SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems Extended Abstract 2017 (CHI EA '17)*, 1700 1707 (Presenter).
- [P5] Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Pan, M.-H., Wang, H.-C., and Hsu, Y.-J. (2015) Let's Solve It Together: Introducing Crowd Workers to Friendsourcing for Improving Creative Design. Presented at *The Taiwan Computer-Human Interaction Workshop 2015 (Tai-CHI '15)* (Presenter).
- [P4] Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Pan, M.-H., Wang, H.-C., and Hsu, Y.-J. (2015). The Price of the Priceless: Understanding Estimated Costs of Work in Friendsourcing. In *The ACM SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems Extended Abstract 2015 (CHI EA '15)*, 1893-1898 (Presenter).
- [P3] Tsai, W.-C., Lee, H.-C., Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Liang, R.-H., and Hsu, Y.-J. (2013). Framing Design of Reminiscence Aids with Transactive Memory Theory. In *The ACM SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems Extended Abstract 2013 (CHI EA '13)*, 331-336.
- [P2] Tsai, W.-C., Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Lee, H.-C., Huang, C.-H., and Hsu, Y.-J. (2012). In Search of Lost Sounds: Designing a Reminiscence Aid in Everyday Soundscape. Presented at *The ACM conference on Designing Interactive Systems 2012 (DIS '12)*.
- [P1] Hsiao, J. C.-Y., Jih, W.-R., and Hsu, Y.-J. (2012). Recognizing Continuous Social Engagement Level in Dyadic Conversation by Using Turn-taking and Speech Emotion Patterns. Presented at AAAI '12 Activity Context Representation Workshop (ACR '12) (Presenter).

Unpublished Theses and Research Reports

- [U3] Hsiao, J. C.-Y. (2018). Social Network Matters: Opportunities for Technologies to Support Immigrants' Jobseeking. Field Prelim, School of Information, Univ. of Michigan.
- [U2] Hsiao, J. C.-Y. (2017). Can People-Nearby Applications Benefit Newly-Arrived Immigrants? An Exploratory Study. *Pre-candidacy research paper*, School of Information, Univ. of Michigan.
- [U1] Hsiao, J. C.-Y. (2012). Assessing Engagement in Conversation by Hierarchically Decomposing Emotion and Interaction. *Master's Thesis*, Dept. of Computer Science and Information Engineering (CSIE), Natl. Taiwan Univ.

RECENT PROJECTS

Designing Social Technologies to Support Newly Arrived Immigrants' Adaptation

Research Leader

Summer 2016 - Present

Exploring socio-technical factors that affect recent immigrants' engagement in using social applications to interact with ethnically mixed user communities, and designing technology interventions that address these factors.

Designing Next-Generational Employment Tools for Underserved Job Seekers

Research Leader

Fall 2018 - Present

Designing, deploying, and investigating novel employment tools' influences on resource-constrained job seekers' job search.

Exploring Information Needs Inspired by Email

Research Leader

Summer 2020

Exploring the information-seeking behaviors that are inspired by email content and contextual factors that associated with these information needs.

Investigating Factors Influencing Participation in the Sharing Economy

Research Assistant

Fall 2017 - Spring 2018

Examining the effects of online trust, demographics, and digital literacy on people's participating in the digital sharing economy.

Discovering People-Nearby Applications' Potential Benefits for People who Face Life Transitions

Research Leader

Fall 2015 - Spring 2016

Studying how people who are new to an area use people-nearby applications' (PNAs) to develop social capital and what are the concerns associated to their use.

HONOR

Graham Sustainability Institute, University of Michigan

Ann Arbor, MI, USA

Dow Sustainability Doctoral Fellowship

2020

Was granted \$15,000 for research on designing social technologies to support immigrants' adaptation and local communities' sustainability; Only ten UM doctoral candidates were granted with the fellowship.

University of Michigan

Ann Arbor, MI, USA

Rackham Pre-candidate Research Grant

2016

Was granted \$1,500 for conducting research on the project that explores immigrants' social technology use for adaptation.

Dept. CSIE, Natl. Taiwan Univ.

Taipei, Taiwan

Graduation Representative

2012

Was chosen as the recognized master's student for leadership and active participation in student affairs of the department

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

UX Research & Consumer Insights Team, Verizon Media

Academic Collaboration Program, USA

Academic Research Collaborator

09/2020 - Present

Extending the internship project by submitting the project results to academic conferences (Research Manager: Frank Bentley)

Social Innovations Group, School of Information, Univ. of Michigan

Ann Arbor, MI, USA

Graduate Student Research Assistant

09/2015 – present

Lead research projects of the Social Innovations Group (SIG), which are focused on designing technologies to help low-resourced populations seek employment and education (Advisor: Dr. Tawanna R. Dillahunt)

UX Research & Consumer Insights Team, Verizon Media

Internship (Virtual), USA

UX Research Intern

06/2020 - 08/2020

Led a project on exploring information needs inspired by email by conducting a two-week diary study and multiple online surveys (Research Manager: Frank Bentley)

UX Team, Intel-NTU IoX Center

Taipei, Taiwan

Research Assistant

07/2014 - 07/2015

Carried out research on user experience and natural user interface under smart environment as the only M.S. member in the team (Advisor: Dr. Bing-Yu Chen)

Workshop Organizer

03/2015 - 05/2015

Organized the collaborative workshop on design thinking of Stanford d.school and National Taiwan University IoX Center

Collaborative & Social Computing Lab, Dept. CS, Natl. Tsing-Hua Univ.

Hsinchu, Taiwan

Visiting Research Assistant

07/2014 - 07/2015

Led a project on friendsourcing, aiming to understand how social capital works when a SNS user requests resources on her/his own social network (Advisor: Dr. Hao-Chuan Wang)

Intelligent Agents Lab, Dept. CSIE, Natl. Taiwan Univ.

Taipei, Taiwan

System Administrator

03/2011 - 07/2013

Managed devices and web services for 30+ lab members

PROFESSIONAL SERVICES

Professional Events & Activities

ACM MobileHCI 2019

09/2017 - 10/2019

Student Volunteer Chair

Taiwan CHI 2015

01/2015 - 07/2015

Organizing Committee

OpenHCI Workshop 2014 (student-organized workshop on HCI in Taiwan)

01/2014 - 07/2014

Steering Committee

OpenHCI Workshop 2013

01/2013 - 07/2013

Program Chair

PROFESSIONAL SERVICES (Cont.)

Social Events & Activities

OpenHCI Workshop 2011

01/2011 - 07/2011

Registration and Volunteer Chair

Univ. of Michigan, School of Information

08/2018 - 07/2019

Doctoral Committee - Student Representative

First Taiwan Night at CSCW

2019

Organizing Committee

Annual Taiwan Night at CHI

2015 - 2018

Organizing Committee

Mandatory Military Service

Taiwan

Company Chief Consultant (Second Lieutenant)

2013 - 2014

Handled psychological consulting, human resources management, and welfare of a military company with 40+ members

Peer Reviewer

ACM CHI 2017 - 2020; ACM CSCW 2017, 2018, 2020; ACM MobileHCI 2018 & 2019; ACM TEI 2017

Conference Student Volunteer

ACM CSCW 2018, 2019; ACM COMPASS 2018; ACM CHI 2017

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant/Graduate Student Instructor

School of Information, Univ. of Michigan

Winter 2018

SI-622: Usability Testing Instructor: Prof. Jovojeet Pal

School of Information, Univ. of Michigan

Fall 2017

SI-501: Contextual Inquiry Instructor: Prof. Kentaro Toyama

Dept. CSIE, Natl. Taiwan Univ. &

Dept. Design, Natl. Taiwan Univ. of Tech. and Sci.

Spring 2013

Advanced Human-Computer Interface/User-Oriented Innovation Design

Instructor: Prof. Hsien-Hui Tang & Prof. Mike Y. Chen

Dept. CSIE, Natl. Taiwan Univ.

Fall 2011

Introduction to Computer Science Instructor: Prof. Jane Yung-Jen Hsu

Student Team Coach

OpenHCI Workshop 2011

07/2011

SPEAKING ENGAGEMENT

Invited Speaker

Lightning Speaker

School of Information, Univ. of Michigan

SI699: Mastery User Experience Research and Design

12/2019 Univ. of Michigan

iDEI: Talks at the Intersection of Information, Diversity, Equity & Inclusion

10/2018